Guide to the Arnold Johnson Papers TAM.137
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Series IV: Political Activities, 1957-1979
  Johnson's legislative and public relations activities for the communist party are documented through speeches and clippings, and his runs for office in New York mainly through clippings. There is interesting documentation of Johnson's trips to communist countries in Europe and to the Soviet Union; folders 7-9 and 15-17 provide insights into these travels both through Johnson's notes and his correspondence with Aurelia. There is little other background material, clippings for example, to further document these trips. Also of interest is the material relating to Johnson's refusal to register as a member of communist party under the McCarran Act in 1962, and his refusal to respond to the subpoena issued by the House Committee on Internal Security in 1970 (which was investigating the group New Mobilization Against the War in Vietnam). Both these incidents, which were never brought to trial, indicate Johnson's continued resoluteness in his beliefs in the freedom of speech. The folder of letters from Lee Harvey Oswald, mostly requesting basic information about the Communist Party, but also providing some description of Oswald's time spent in the Soviet Union and his interest in the Cuban cause, are worthy of note. Other principal correspondents include William Z. Foster and Eugene Dennis (box 4, folder 3, two brief letters).
  - Elizabeth Gurley Flynn candidate for City Council New York - campaign speeches, flyers, clippings, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Statement by the New York State CP to the Independent Socialist Electoral Conference, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, includes McCarran Act (1962), 1958-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eastland Dodd Committee hearings - correspondence and statement, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Candidate for Congress, New York - clippings, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Candidate for Congress, New York - press releases, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Trip to communist countries - notes, memorabilia, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Trip to communist countries - notes, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Trip to communist countries - correspondence, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speech “Anti Communism in the USA”, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lee Harvey Oswald - correspondence, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Clippings, 1964-1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pacem in Terris - Peace on Earth, International Convention, New York City, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Trip to communist countries with Gus Hall - notes, speeches, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Trip to communist countries with Gus hall - notes, correspondence, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Trip to communist countries with Gus hall - correspondence, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Elections 1968 - reports, speeches (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - World Assembly for Peace and College Colloquy - correspondence, notes, printed material, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Democratic Peoples Republic of Korea - statement, newspaper Poyong Yang Times, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - New Mobilization against the War in Vietnam and House Internal Security Committee (HISC)-speeches, statements, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Clippings - candidate for Senate, HISC indictment, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - CP material - speeches, correspondence, printed material, 1972-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Clippings, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - First Congress of CP of Cuba - speech, notes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Clippings, articles - includes Cuba Congress, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Smith Act fine contributions, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Handwritten notes, undated (1960's) (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - National Convention CPUSA - speeches, reports (William Foster), articles (not by Arnold Johnson)., 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Elections, conventions, hearings - speeches, statements, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Subversive Activities Control Board vs Johnson, McCarran Act - printed material, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Oswald, Lee Harvey - correspondence, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4A)
  - Speeches (Johnson) - May Day and Election, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Vietnam War - articles and press releases, 1966-1970 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Trip to Democratic Republic of Vietnam - notes, speeches, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series V: Biographical, Personal and Ephemera, circa 1928-1989
  This series contains biographical information on Arnold Johnson, some personal material of Aurelia Ricci, and further documentation of their strong bond (through correspondence). There is also a substantial amount of correspondence and greetings indicating the Johnsons' large numbers of contacts, in and out of the Communist Party. Particularly useful are folders 12 and 19 which provide the bulk of the biographical material on Arnold Johnson. The handwritten notebook in folder 19 was apparently an outline for a book; although brief it provides interesting insights into Johnson's road to the Communist Party and his satisfaction with the “communist life”.
  - Aurelia Ricci, Summer Schools for Women, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Aurelia Ricci (later Johnson), 1931-1933 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Personal (Arnold and Aurelia), 1971, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Diplomas, 1931, 1932 (Box MSXOS003, Folder 1)
  - 70th Birthday Tribute, Correspondence, Clippings, Flyers, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Union Theological Seminary, Correspondence, 1974, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Get Well Correspondence, 1977, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Resignation, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Greetings, Invitations from CP Ambassadors, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Gift of Arnold Johnson Library to Ohio State University, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Biographical, Recollections and Obituaries, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Series VI: Artifacts and Photographs, circa 1928-1975
  Series VI: Artifacts and Photographs contains materials from the Communist Party USA, from the international communist parties, and personal memorabilia and photographs. Included in this series is a small photograph album containing photographs of Johnson and others taken during Sherwood Eddy’s “American Seminar” in the summers of 1929 and 1930. Individual and group photographs from the 1930s through early 1950s depict prominent members and leaders of the CPUSA and portraits of the second group of Smith Act defendants. Also included are photographs and a photograph album of CPUSA trips to Europe and the USSR in the 1960s. Additionally, there are photographs of CPUSA demonstrations and events. There is a box of photographs and memorabilia from the 1st Cuban Communist Party Congress in 1975. Additionally, there is a box of commemorative medallions and pins from a variety of international Communist parties. Also included in this series are photographs from summer schools for women attended by Aurelia Ricci Johnson in the late 1920s and early 1930s; there captions on reverse side of most photographs. Additionally, there are two photograph albums of Johnson’s artwork, one reel to reel (likely a recording of an Arnold Johnson speech), and a diploma and ceremonial hammer from California Christian College.
  - Audiotape, Gavel, Photograph Albums, and Communist Party of Cuba Memorabilia, circa 1929-1975 (Box 5)
  - Medallions and Pins, undated (Box 6)
  - Photograph Albums and Photographs, circa 1928-1975 (Box 7)